Morning, Max.
Thank you for joining us.
Thank you.
We've got your written submission and the supplementary as well.
Yep.
We've got you down for five minutes, and we're in your hands, okay?
Okay.
Good morning.
Thank you for giving me an opportunity to speak.
Public sentiment concerning justice is
primarily formulated around the question: who gets what sentence?
I base my concern about cultural reporting and the industry
around it, and how it stands in relation to law,
society, and justice,
and why it is a threat to these things.
There is a preventative feature to the design of law of a threat, and
the state,
in criminalizing conduct, issues a legal threat.
There is a presumption inside of law of a certain concept
about human nature that is a function of law, in that people are
assumed to be moral agents, and I uphold this
ideal.
The repentant actor finds
his self-evaluation confirmed in the disapproval by
others, and the defiant one is made to feel and understand the
disapproval of others.
It is not a matter of in calculating
that the conduct is wrong, but rather that the penal censure
embodied serves to appeal to people's cause of the
conduct as being wrongful,
and a moral agent
given
on this grounds to desist through
a preventative censor.
To remove moral agency is to treat an offender or potential
offender as tigers might be treated in a circus.
A being there who needs to be restrained, intimidated, and
contained into compliance.
It is as much our ideas about law itself which are important.
As
this does a grave injustice to a person's dignity in reducing them in this way.
How much more does it attack the justice of our
system?
And I'm confident in my argument because it is defensible,
much less has the backing of public sentiment in resisting
encroachment on justice around the relevance of
cultural reporting and its relationship to law,
whereby extraneous circumstances are used to mitigate or
massage the culpability of the defendant.
Here I cite the example of the recent court case
involving Ilepseani
Mapu and the public outrage at the light sentencing given.
As the moral authority of the court goes, so goes the nation,
in that there are threats to our justice system that are
not only
external and obvious, but subtle when conceptual and from
within. I'd like to close by saying that there is no greater
injustice that we could commit to the dignity of a person by robbing
them of moral agency.
Thank you, Max.
Doesn't look like we have any questions from members, but we really appreciate your
time this morning, and thanks for coming before us.
Thank you.
We've got Mark now joining us online. Thank you.
Morning, Mark.
Hi, can you hear me?
We can, and we can see you. That's great.
We've got you down for five minutes, and we've read your written submission.
If you just want to leave a little bit of time at the end, there may be some
questions.
Sure.
Yeah, so mainly the submission was around the Coroners Act, and it's great adding
nurse practitioners into that.
But whilst you've got the CPMIP and the Triple PNR Act there as
well, it'd be great if nurse practitioners could be added into those.
So with the Triple PNR Act,
because we're authorized prescribers, we are constantly assessing people's capacity
to treatment. That lets down medications that we're prescribing, or them what
they're going to be used for, how to take them, what they,
et cetera, and their ability to retain that information and use that information.
So when it comes to the Triple PNR Act, because it's such an old piece of
legislation, it came out 12 years before nurse practitioners
were invented, as it were.
In legislation currently, it allows for courts to use their discretion
to take reports from nurse practitioners as to somebody's capacity.
We've got 77 mental health nurse practitioners.
We're very used to dealing with the family court.
They're used to dealing with us, so the judge is quite used to seeing reports from
us in the mental health sphere around people's capacity
to consent to treatment,
capacity full stop.
But you've got issues with
places like the public trust who will reject reports from nurse practitioners from
aged care, from primary care, because they're not used to dealing with them,
and the legislation basically says it should be a medical practitioner
doing it. So if that amendment could be added in, that would be great.
It would make a lot of sense. It brings it in line with other pieces of
legislation. And obviously, as the number of MPs in
primary care and aged care continue to increase-
That it just breaks down another barrier for people.
In a trial, someone's capacity is
going. The other bit of legislation you got before you is the Criminal
Proceedings Mentally Impaired Persons Act, and again, this is somewhere where
we've got 77 mental health nurse practitioners, and
they could do those capacity assessments because, again, we do them for the Mental
Health Act and the fitness to plead and the fitness to stand
trial.
There's a massive backlog in section
38 assessments, which causes problems for the courts, causes problems
for the prison system, and causes problems for the patients or for the
prisoners as well because they can't access the treatment they need because they're
awaiting
the assessment. So if nurse practitioners could be added to the definition of
health assessor in that act, that would again free up a lot of
capacity because like I said, we've got 77 at the moment, mental
health nurse practitioners, and we're adding about five to 10 a year.
So that's a huge number of people that you could bring on stream
to do these assessments.
Happy to take questions.
Thanks, Mark. We do have a couple of questions. We'll start with Lawrence Sunam.
Thank you, Chair. Thank you, Mark, for that submission.
I'm just trying to pull up,
you're right, we've seen in some of the other legislation in terms of just
alignment in term with medical practitioners as well as nurse
practitioners. My question is, would you
think that mental health practitioners should also be
included? Anyone else I can think of from
HCPAA, and you mentioned briefly, but would you
elaborate on how that would alleviate some of the bottleneck we're currently
seeing and the load, the capacity and load in general if we're
adding nurse practitioners into that?
Yeah, so what you tend to find is that if there's a report done
by a nurse practitioner for the Triple PNR act that gets rejected, all that happens
is that a doctor will sign it. This is the workaround, because the
doctors trust the nurse practitioner's assessment, they trust their judgment, they
trust their ability to assess capacity.
So it's kind of there's a workaround, and it doesn't help
with transparency of practice. So that's the main thing.
And basically, yeah, and we've got over 1,000
nurse practitioners, and if you're bringing those guys
into the pool of people who can do these reports, it's going to make a
massive difference to the bottleneck because
it's a big population, and it's increasing by about 100 nurse
practitioners a year.
Dan Rosewell.
Thanks, Chair. Just with your point around nurse practitioners having the same
skill set required to undertake these assessments, I was just
wondering what additional safeguards, if any,
would you support to ensure the assessment quality
remains consistent across those different professions?
That's an interesting question. So at the moment, I'm a
responsible clinician under the Mental Health Act, so I have the same powers and
responsibilities as my consultant psychiatrist colleagues.
And the
number of complaints about nurse practitioners are very-- so the
quality is great.
If you look at the United States, about 2% of
malpractice cases
are against nurse practitioners, and even when those numbers
doubled, it still stayed at only 2% of all
malpractice cases. So, we practice cautiously, we practice safely.
We're very mindful of our area of practice, and we stay within that.
So, I'm very much a specialist mental health NP, so I wouldn't stray
into respiratory medicine or anything like that.
So we're very conscious of what we do.
And the
quality is there. The research has shown that we have the same
skill set, we have the same level of standards.
So
there's no evidence to the contrary, basically.
Thank you.
Thank you. And we've just got one final question from Joseph Mooney.
Thank you. Mine's a sort of follow on from Dan's point, actually, in a way.
I worked for a number of years in the courts, and particularly
Manukau and Auckland District Courts.
I repeatedly had clients
who I had serious concerns about and got an initial assessment from
the mental health nurse who
said, mental health nurses, I should say, who said it was behavioral.
I didn't accept their analysis and asked the courts for a section 38 report.
And after getting a section 38 report, every single time it came back that there
was actually some serious mental health
capacity issues at play. So
my
question would be sort of follow on from Dan, how do we ensure that we get that-
Yeah
...
a rigorous oversight and analysis?
Sure. Yeah, so if you look at the nurses you'd be talking about in court, they
would be registered nurses. So they would be court
liaison nurses. So nurse practitioner is a different scope entirely.
We've got a clinical master's degree.
So we have had additional extra
training to gain that skill set, and we
work very much within a multidisciplinary team
setting.
I'm off now to the MDT with my two consultant colleagues.
So we have that oversight, we have that liaison,
so we're not completely independent and autonomous, but we do
have to have quite rigorous training to be able to do those assessments.
And like I said, a number of us within
mental health and responsible clinicians,
a vast majority of us have also been approved by the Director of Area Mental
Health Services to be section 10 approved, which means we do the initial
assessment for Mental Health Act, same as our consultant psychiatrist
colleagues. Myself, personally, I've just been down to Invercargill covering down
there,
and I've been covering the acute inpatient ward alongside a consultant
psychiatrist. I've covered the duty psychiatrist role overnight
for the entirety of the kind of Southland,
Queenstown, Wanaka area.
So, if we didn't have that - skill set and for those colleagues,
we wouldn't be doing those things.
Thank you, Mark. Really appreciate you joining us this morning and giving us plenty
of food for thought, so really do appreciate it. Thank you. Thanks for your work.
Yeah, just-
Okay, now we're going to have Rex joining us, who's going to be joining us online
as well.
Morning, Rex.
Good morning.
Thank you very much for joining us.
We've got you for five minutes, and we've read your submission. Over to you.
Thank you very much. Under family law, one of the amendments is
more flexibility in paying for cultural, medical, psychiatric, or
psychological reports.
I believe that there is a cottage industry that's grown up around cultural
reports, and the wrong people are getting off just on the say-so
of people. People are being paid big money to provide a cultural
report. We've all got a sad story. It might explain things,
but it doesn't excuse a crime. I would top the cultural
report fee payable as $100,
and that anybody making a cultural report needs to know that person for
10 years or more. How can they provide any
thoughts on anybody if they're just coming into their office and telling them,
"Oh, oh, this is what happened to me"? There's no verification.
I don't believe in cultural reports for that.
The Coroners Act, you're going to increase coroners from 22 to 26.
That's welcome, because there's quite a backlog.
I notice you've already changed the lawyers and coroners.
No medical professionals, no medical practitioners, just lawyers and
barristers.
Bit of a shame.
Now, the last thing I'd like to say, because I'm not here for long,
is you
want to reduce the health assessor reports for people
proving mental impairment from two to one.
Now, who guards the guards? That's a terrible lack of
safeguarding. And what's a health assessor? Is that a nurse?
No, it's meant to be a psychiatrist or a
psychologist. And the previous speaker, nurse practitioners,
you got all sorts of bits of paper. That's a cool story, bro, but you're not a
doctor. You're not a psychologist.
You're not a psychiatrist. If you are not registered as
that, you have no right to speak on somebody's mental impairment
according to the law as it stands. And to remove that safeguarding, there's checks
but no balances.
So you're going to have the say-so of one person.
I believe there needs to be two, and you mustn't change
that. I don't answer questions. You're here to answer to us,
so please take note of what I've said. Good day.
Thanks, Rex. Thank you very much for joining us.
Okay, that concludes our hearings on the bill, so we will just shift
into private